<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Good nevves from Alsasia and the Palatinate, the fift of Iune The abstract of three seuerall letters, the one sent from Elsas in Alsatia, where Leopold vsed to keepe his court, the other from Hagenaw which was besieged by him the last from Franke-fort, containing the King of Bohemia's pursute of his victory obtained against the Emperours forces vnder Leopoldus. Afterwards the marching of the Kings forces vnder Count Mansfield, towards the Landtgraue of Darmestats country, with the abstract of another letter sent from the land of Hessen, relating the aduentures which happened to the Duke Christian of Brunswicke in his iourney towards the Palatinate. The late proceedings in the Low-countries, France, and diuers other parts in Germanie.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08157</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.51</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 538</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104393</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840131</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840131</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4603</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08157)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4603)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 819:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Good nevves from Alsasia and the Palatinate, the fift of Iune The abstract of three seuerall letters, the one sent from Elsas in Alsatia, where Leopold vsed to keepe his court, the other from Hagenaw which was besieged by him the last from Franke-fort, containing the King of Bohemia's pursute of his victory obtained against the Emperours forces vnder Leopoldus. Afterwards the marching of the Kings forces vnder Count Mansfield, towards the Landtgraue of Darmestats country, with the abstract of another letter sent from the land of Hessen, relating the aduentures which happened to the Duke Christian of Brunswicke in his iourney towards the Palatinate. The late proceedings in the Low-countries, France, and diuers other parts in Germanie.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 18, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B[ernard] A[lsop] for Nicholas Bourne, and Thomas Archer, and are to be solde at the Exchange, and in Popes Head-pallace,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 538 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Germany --  History --  1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4603:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4603:1"/>
            <p>GOOD NEVVES FROM ALSASIA AND THE PALATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, the fift of Iune.</p>
            <p>THE ABSTRACT OF THREE SEVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall letters, the one ſent from <hi>Elſas</hi> in <hi>Alſatia,</hi> where <hi>Leopold</hi> vſed to keepe his Court, the other from <hi>Hagenaw</hi> which was beſieged by him the laſt from <hi>Franke-fort,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the King of <hi>Bohemias</hi> purſute of his Victory obtained againſt the Emperours forces vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Leopoldus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AFTERWARDS THE MARCHING OF THE Kings forces vnder Count Mansfield, towards the Landtgraue of Darmeſtats Country, with the Abſtract of another letter ſent from the Land of Heſſen, relating the aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which hath happened to the Duke Chriſtian of Brunſwicke in his iourney towards the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate.</p>
            <p>The late proceedings in the Low-countries, France, and diuers other parts in Germanie.</p>
            <p>At London printed by <hi>E. A.</hi> for <hi>Nicholas Bourne,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Archer,</hi> and are to be ſolde at the Exchange, and in Popes Head-pallace. 1622.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:4603:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4603:2"/>
            <head>AN ABSTRACT OVT OF LETTERS WRITTEN FROM ELSAS AND STRABVRGH, bearing date of the 22. of May. 1622.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Towne of Hagenaw being ſtrongly beſiege by the Arch Duke <hi>Leopoldus,</hi> and vpon the 16. of May, all the ſconces about it taken by him, but yet with great loſſe of many of his men, preſently there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he ſent certaine meſſengers to Strasburgh, who for the taking in of the Towne made ſute vnto them to ſend him ſome prouiſion for the ſame, hoping vpon the 17. of May, to take it; and for that it is the Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all chamber, the ſayd Arch Duke doubted not, but that the Counſell of the Citie of Strasburgh, would not ſpare to ſtretch out their meanes to helpe him, where vpon the ſayd Counſell taking no ſpeedy reſolution, but rather for a while conſulted what they ſhould doe, ſent ſome powder, bullets, and prouant vnto him. But not long after, newes was brought that <hi>Fredericke</hi> King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and the Earle of Mansfield with their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie were not farre from Hagenaw, and that 1000. cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baten moſt cuiraſſers, that were ſent by the Arch Duke to ſtop Mansfields paſſage, were ſet vpon and fought with all by <hi>Colonell Ouertront,</hi> in which fight 500. of them were ſlaine, many taken priſoners, and the reſt ſcattered and diſperſed abroad. And vpon the 17. day of May in the euening, ſome of them that fled, got to <hi>Leopoldus</hi> Campe, and certified him thereof, counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him to make preparation to fly away, whereupon
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4603:3"/>he preſently ſet fire on his Tents, and ſo went away, leauing the Towne at libertie againe. But the Earle of Mansfield, with all ſpeede and diligence with 10000. men, followed him, and as many of his ſouldiers as he could get, he ſlew, and diſperſing <hi>Leopoldus</hi> Armie tooke from him great ſtore of powder, bullets, pillage: and ſome prouant.</p>
            <p>And vpon the 18. and 19. of May the ſayd Earle of Mansfield purſuing the chaſe, marched further towards Truſenheim, where <hi>Leopoldus</hi> ſouldiers had caſt vp a ſconſe vpon the Rhin, and had fortified the ſame, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in many of the ſayd ſouldiers had ſaued themſelues, to the number of 2000. men, and had prepared boates ready, if they were aſſailed, to ſet them ouer the Rhin, but Mansfield encloſed them round about, and cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the boates, and carrying them away, gaue them an alarme, and entring in vpon them, ſlew them all, and therein found great ſtore of bootie, of the which euery ſouldier was ſuffered to take whatſoeuer he could for himſelfe.</p>
            <p>After that vpon the 20. of May many of Mansfields ſouldiers marched along by Strasburgh, to ouerrun all the Countrie of Elſas, and all thoſe places that <hi>Leopol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> had taken in, which put <hi>Leopoldus</hi> ſouldiers in ſuch a feare that they knew not where to ſtay, nor to hide themſelues, and if it had not beene for a bridge that was broken downe, whereby <hi>Colonell Ouertr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt</hi> came halfe an houre to late, he had taken <hi>Leopoldus</hi> himſelfe, the King of Bohemia went perſonally to goe into Strasburgh, from whence <hi>Leopoldus</hi> meſſengers much grieued, road haſtily away, and what ſoeuer they had obtained of the Towne, Mansfield had the moſt part thereof.</p>
            <p>Touching the Marquis of <hi>Doerlach</hi> his ouerthrow
<pb facs="tcp:4603:3"/>was not ſo great, as it was thought to haue beene, who with the firſt is to enter into the field againe with ten thouſand men. It is ſayd, that the Duke of <hi>Bauaria</hi> wrote vnto him, to make good his loſſes, and to giue him all againe that was taken from him, if hee would leaue the field, and diſcharge his ſouldiers; but hee roundly and roughly refuſed to doe ſo, and for anſwer ſent him word, that he hoped by Armes to recouer his loſſes againe.</p>
            <p>Letters of the 21. alſo certifie, That after <hi>Leopoldus</hi> Colonels and Souldiers vnderſtood, that <hi>Mansfields</hi> Armie ſtill marched vpward, and behaued themſelues ſo valiantly, and with ſuch courage againſt them, they would not ſtay for him, but retired in flight to <hi>Elſas, Sabren, Moltheim</hi> and <hi>Dackſteim;</hi> but their carriage, waggons and women, were all left behinde them, which <hi>Mansfield</hi> ſet vpon, and ranſacking them, tooke many chaines of gold and jewells from them, but did no hurt to the women, but tooke their quarter from them, and there ſtayed.</p>
            <p>Other Letters of the 22. certifie, That the ſame day ſix cornets of <hi>Leopoldus</hi> horſemen came to <hi>Mitle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinsbergen,</hi> that had conuoyed their Colonell <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> but as then hee was not perſonally with them: men wondered that <hi>Mansfield</hi> had not ſet on them, they ſaid, that in the ſpace of three dayes, they had neyther eaten nor ſeene any bread, and that they had ſaued themſelues heere and there in the woods, and for a time got fother from the ſaid Towne, and after that went to <hi>Strasburgh,</hi> being not farre from thence, where ſtaying about the length of a great peece of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance ſhot, without the Towne, they ſent a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet to offer their ſeruice vnto them, but the magiſtrates thanked them, and made them anſwere, that they had
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4603:4"/>no need of horſemen, whereupon they intreated the Magiſtrates, that they might be permitted (if any of <hi>Mansfields</hi> colonells were in the Towne) to offer their ſeruice vnto them, and ſo to yeelde themſelues vnto him, which they graunted. But Colonell <hi>Ouertront</hi> with his brother and couſen that then were there, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thereof, rode preſently vnto them, with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine horſemen, and entertaining them with a friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly countenance, asked them why they would no more ſerue their Lord, they tolde him, that they had not receiued any money in twelue or eighteene moneths, as alſo, that their Colonell had left them, and that therefore they were diſcharged of their oathes, and prayed that they might bee entertained in <hi>Mansfields</hi> Army. The Duke of <hi>Saxon</hi> in the meane time came to diſſwade thoſe horſe, when they were on the poynt of changing their Spaniſh Coſaques, &amp; ſo was taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner: he is of the houſe of <hi>Saxen, Lawenberg,</hi> his grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father was he that was depriued of the Electorate; hee pretends himſelfe to be no lawfull priſoner, hauing quitted a Regiment hee had in <hi>Hungarie,</hi> about ſeuen moneths ſince, that hee was at <hi>Strasburgh,</hi> in expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of being receiued into the French Kings ſeruice. That hee came out of the Port of <hi>Strasburgh</hi> to ſpeake with a Captaine of his brothers Regiment, to reſerue himſelfe for <hi>Fraunce</hi> if the Regiment disbanded. His Brother is in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> where hee hath two other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments, one of horſe and another of foote. But <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertrant</hi> alleadgeth that he is in <hi>Leopoldus</hi> ſeruice, and came out to diſſwade the Regiment from disbanding, and that hee clapt betweene him and the Port. The Duke ſaith within the Centrie, but without the Turne pike. What King <hi>Fredericke</hi> will doe with him, wee ſhall hereafter heare.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:4603:4"/>
            <p>The ſaid 6 Coronets of horſmen ſaid, that the next day, 5 Coronets of <hi>Cratiſche</hi> horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and a regiment of footemen more would alſo yeeld vnto <hi>Mansfield,</hi> and enter into pay with him. It is thought the whole army will riſe and march towards <hi>Elſus Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beren, Moltiſheim, Dacſtein</hi> and other places, for that the ſaid townes haue want of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition and prouant, becauſe they were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to ſend it all to the campe before <hi>Hage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naw:</hi> it is dangerous trauelling in theſe parts round about: and it is to be feared that all <hi>Flſas</hi> will yeeld, or forcibly be brought vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der King <hi>Fredericks</hi> command. The Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke <hi>Leopoldus</hi> ſaued himſelfe in <hi>Freiburge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further, letters of the 22 of May certifie, that thereabouts they haue ſtrengthened themſelues with a few footmen that fled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from <hi>Hagenaw,</hi> with 5 field peeces, and in great danger; for the Marquis of <hi>Durlach</hi> who with 7000 foote and 2000 horſemen is entred againe into the field, and hauing diſcharged and paid all his men, hath again entertained them in King <hi>Fredericks</hi> name.</p>
            <p>The relieuing and beating away of the army before <hi>Hagenaw,</hi> is confirmed by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:4603:5"/>letters: they vvithin the towne could not haue holden out aboue 2 dayes longer: the Archduke <hi>Leopoldus</hi> in his retraite loſt a great peece of ordinance, 26 hundred weight of pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, great ſtore of munition, bullets &amp; match, as alſo all his cariage, and 500 men that vvere ſlaine, the reſt that ſaued themſelues in the flight, went to <hi>Litchtnaw,</hi> and further vpvvard to <hi>Wilſteden,</hi> &amp; are gone ouer the Rhine, &amp; in the ditches about the ſuburbes, vvhile the gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in <hi>Hagenaw</hi> valiantly defended themſelues: many of <hi>Leopoldus</hi> ſouldiers vvere ſtaine in the approch. And newes is now come that <hi>Waſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naw,</hi> Colonell <hi>Crats,</hi> vvith 6 cornets of horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men &amp; 2 regiments of footmen, haue left <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poldus,</hi> &amp; are falne to <hi>Mansfields</hi> ſide, and that foure cornets of horſemen more &amp; a regiment of footmen vvould doe the like.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <head>An extract of a letter ſent from Hagenaw, dated the <hi>19</hi> of May, <hi>1622.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The 17 of May the Earle of <hi>Mansfield</hi> came before <hi>Hagenaw,</hi> to releaſe the towne from the ſiege that vvas laid about it by the Archduke <hi>Leopoldus;</hi> and therefore the ſaid Archduke had
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4603:5"/>beaten downe the bridge ouer the vvater to hinder the enemies approch; but they vvithin in the ſpace of three houres repaired it againe: but vvhen the Archduke vnderſtood of the enemies approch vvith ſo great forces, in the morning at 6 of the clocke he left the towne, &amp; in great confuſion fled away, leauing behind him 4000 loaues of bread &amp; good ſtore of vvine &amp; all other prouiſion. <hi>Mansfields</hi> horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſet upon the <hi>Leopoldians,</hi> &amp; kild all they could find, and tooke much booty from them, one vvaggon being laden full of bandoleers for peeces.</p>
            <p>The 18 of May <hi>Mansfields</hi> ſouldiers vvent to <hi>Buſwild</hi> a mile from <hi>Hagenaw,</hi> vvherein vvas 60 ſouldiers that yeelded unto them, there they found all maner of munition &amp; a great peece of Ordinance, ſome peeces of Ordinance were ſunke, and <hi>Mansfields</hi> ſouldiers were before <hi>Cotten,</hi> &amp; as it is ſaid haue taken it, &amp; purſued after <hi>Leopoldus</hi> ſouldiers, and ſome of the ſaid <hi>Leopoldus</hi> ſouldiers themſelues did robbe and ranſacke many of his vvaggons, and tooke what they could cary away, the reſt they left for <hi>Mansfield.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:4603:6"/>
            <head>An extract out of a letter ſent from Frankfor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>29</hi> of May, <hi>1622.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>That which was laſt written touching the breaking vp of the ſiege before the towne of <hi>Hagenaw,</hi> and the ouerthrow of <hi>Leopoldus,</hi> is confirmed out of <hi>Elſas</hi> and <hi>Strasburch,</hi> after that the towne of <hi>Hagenaw</hi> vvas beſieged by <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poldus</hi> vvith an army of 12000 men horſe and foote, and the ſame had by him bin battered eight dayes together: they vvithin iſſued ſo valiantly out, and fought ſo couragiouſly within, that before it an Italian Colonell and a Lieutenant Colonell, called <hi>Fels</hi> vvere taken priſoners, vvho vvere much fauoured by <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poldus,</hi> and a 1000 men vvere ſlaine by them, as alſo the 1000 Crabaten that the ſaid Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duke ſent to the towne of <hi>Weiſſenburg</hi> to take it, vvere alſo by the Earle of <hi>Mansfield</hi> moſt part ſlaine and diſperſed, and yet dayly ſome of them are kild by the peſants.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> vvith the Earle of <hi>Mansfield</hi> and 15000 horſe and foote coming to <hi>Hagenaw,</hi> the <hi>Leopoldians</hi> vvere already fled, leauing all their cariage and vvaggons vvith munition behind them, and here and there ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued themſelues, as they beſt could doe it: but
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4603:6"/>the Colonels <hi>Ouertr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt</hi> and <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gen</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they vvere fled, preſently followed after them vvith their horſemen, and kild many of them: vvhich purſuite continued for the ſpace of three dayes till <hi>Leopoldus</hi> ſouldiers vvere dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen further away: and in <hi>Truſen hey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> vvood the ſaid Earle of <hi>Mansfield</hi> encloſed 16 com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of Italian horſemen that could not get out; how they ſped, it is yet no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> certainly knowne, but it is to be feared that few of them vvould eſcape avvay.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Biſweyld</hi> 60 of them alſo ſaued th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in the caſtle; vvith thoſe that vvere <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Netherlanders;</hi> good quarter vvas holden, but the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Wallons</hi> vvere all ſlaine, for amongſt them they held no quarter: in that caſtle they found 460 vveight of powder, and at <hi>Brunbt</hi> 300 vveight of powder. Thus <hi>Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poldus</hi> ſouldiers vvere ſcattered abroad, and thoſe that vvere not ſlaine fell from him, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready many cornets of horſe and footmen are entertained by <hi>Mansfield,</hi> and are entred into pay.</p>
            <p>It is ſaids that the Earl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Mansfield</hi> lies round about <hi>Spiers</hi> again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, to let the <hi>Spaniards</hi> that are comming thither from ioyning vvith
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4603:7"/>the <hi>Bauarians,</hi> and to cut them off. It is confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med that the ouerthrow of the Marquis of <hi>Durlach</hi> was not ſo great as it was reported to be: the ſaid Marquis in the beginning hauing had the victory againſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> but his gun pouder being fired, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him againe, yet 2 ſpaniſh Lords were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken priſoners by him, for whom <hi>Monſieur Tilly</hi> offered to releaſe all his priſoners, but the Marquis would not, vnleſſe hee would reſtore his Ordinance and munition alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <head>An abſtract of a letter written from Heſſen the <hi>22</hi> of May, <hi>1622.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>It is reported that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarians</hi> intending to ſet upon the towne of <hi>Paderborme,</hi> from whence the Duke of <hi>Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> was gone; the ſaid Duke thereupon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned backe againe, and as vvee heare hath fought with them, where betweene them there was a great fight, wherein many on both ſides were ſlaine, and that the Duke of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> had the victorie, the certaintie whereof is daily expected: it is ſaid y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is gone
<pb facs="tcp:4603:7"/>with certaine thouſand men towards the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate,</hi> and hath left good gariſons in <hi>Lipſtat</hi> and <hi>Soeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As alſo that upon the 16 of May the ſaid Duke going from <hi>Paterborm</hi> with his army of 20000 men horſe &amp; foot marching to <hi>Eiſvelt,</hi> and hauing made a bridge ouer the <hi>Weſel</hi> at <hi>Hopſel,</hi> the Earle <hi>Stirom</hi> with his horſemen ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the Rereward, being wartered at <hi>Salts Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,</hi> the <hi>Spaniards</hi> &amp; <hi>Bauarians</hi> the night before went thither and made an alarme, ſetting upon the Rereward, &amp; thought to take their cariage; but the Duke preſently relieuing them, kild ſome of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Bauarians,</hi> and tooke ſome priſoners. And ſince we heard that the Elector of <hi>Colen</hi> and the Baron of <hi>Anholt</hi> had an intent to ſet upon the Duke of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> as he marched forward, and to that end ſent 16 companies of horſemen and ſome foote to ſet upon his Rereward; Which the Duke under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, turned back againe, and met with the enemy, hauing eight peeces of Ordinance with him, vvhereupon the enemie furiouſly ſet upon him; and he cauſing his greateſt troupes vvith the peeces to retire, preſently made a lane, and gaue fire to his Ordinance, and
<pb facs="tcp:4603:8"/>and therewith put his enemies in ſuch a feare, that they fled away, vvhom he o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all ſides pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, and ſlue three cornets of horſe, and eight companies of their footmen, vvhich done he followed on his victorie.</p>
            <p>And now vve are certified that the ſaid Duke of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> hath bin at <hi>Hildeſheim</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Biſhop of <hi>Colen,</hi> and hath gotten 2000 weeks Dollers of the Capiall, &amp; as much from the <hi>Iewes</hi> there, for that they hauing taken vp the good mony in the country of <hi>Brunſwik,</hi> cauſed ſuch bad mony to be minted, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by great complaints and hurt enſued. And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that the ſaid Duke went to the ſtift Fulda, and it is ſaid that he is there already, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Abbot and the Capitoll to giue him a great ſumme of mony, from whence he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to go to the Biſhopricke of <hi>Wirtsburg</hi> in <hi>Frankenland,</hi> and alſo to the Biſhop of <hi>Bamburg</hi> and other to viſit them.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid that he left a ſtrong gariſon in <hi>Lip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat</hi> before his d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>parture, being eleuen compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of horſe and footmen, as alſo in the towne of <hi>Ham,</hi> theſe 2 townes are indifferent ſtrong and vvell prouided of all things, ſo that in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine moneths they can want nothing.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:4603:8"/>
            <p>It is certified from <hi>Veni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> that in <hi>Naples</hi> the preparation for the Warre dayly goes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and that they haue great want of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, as alſo that there are Souldiers taken vp in the double Donne of <hi>Millaine</hi> that are to bee ſent againſt thoſe of <hi>Valtolina,</hi> and the Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p>They write from <hi>Vienna</hi> that the ſame day the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour rode to the meeting holden in Oldenburgh, wherein hee is to enter the 20. of May, and that the next Munday enſuing, the Propoſitions ſhall be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, and then thoſe at Lepenburg and Newſtadt ſhall ceaſe, where the Spauſchapper and the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palleſt Lords are altogether aſſembled. With the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour there went 12. Companies of Foot, and two Regiments of Horſmen. That <hi>Bethlem Gabor</hi> the Marqueſſe of Iagarenſdorp and the Earle of Thurne and Hof-kirchen are yet at Grootwerden, and cauſe a great number of Souldiers to march out of Setenber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghen to Caſſan.</p>
            <p>Alſo that the Emperours Generall, the Earle of Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gromont with <hi>Don Balthaſar,</hi> are appointed to goe from thence to the Emperours <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d <hi>Leopoldus</hi> his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in Elſas.</p>
            <p>That ſtill they build vp the new Bulwarkes in Vien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, and it is ſaid that the Suburbs that were laſt markt out ſhall be taken downe againe, and that on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide of the Draw-bridge there ſhall bee a new
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4603:9"/>Towne built, the ground being freely giuen to that vſe.</p>
            <p>The laſt Letter from <hi>Prague</hi> makes mention, that the 1000. Horſemen taken vp by the Duke of Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtein for the Emperour are come into the Gatſer Crays, the Commiſſary of the Muſters chiefe Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant is gone thither to muſter to muſter them, but they will take no other money but rickes Dollars and Golde, there are to goe to the lower Palatinate with the men of <hi>Bechmans</hi> Regiment, and 5. Companies of <hi>Prene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteines</hi> Regiment.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe that the <hi>Dampier</hi> Horſemen, that ſerued at the beginning of the Warre, becauſe that in long time they haue receiued no pay, quarter themſelues at Pilgrimb in Bohemia.</p>
            <p>That in the Commincke Gratſer Territories, there are 3000. Peſants (belonging to the Baron <hi>Datsby</hi>) aſſembled together, who hauing nothing to liue on, nor no meanes left them to Plow and till the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, are reſolutely determined to venture their liues, and to joyne with thoſe that are the ſtrongeſt, it is ſaid that they were moued and ſtirred vp vnto that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion by the young Earle of Thurne, and it is certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, that not long ſince they haue pillaged and ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſackt the Countrey, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d all the wayes 5. myles round about, and haue carryed away all that they could get or come by, and it is reported that the olde Earle of Thurne with ſome thouſands of Walachians, will march through Morauia to relieue his Sonne that is beſieged in Glats.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:4603:9"/>
            <p>It is written from <hi>Cullen,</hi> that the day before the King of Bohemia's-departure, Being the 16. of May, there came an Ambaſſadour vnto him from <hi>Bethlem Gab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi> as alſo from the Marqueſſe of Iagarenſdorp, with Letters containing as it is thought, that hee would make no peace with the Emperour, but would continue the Warre ſtill and holde with the King.</p>
            <p>That the Spaniards inſconce themſelues by Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penheim, and the Bauarians at Gilzerhoorn vpon the Necker, 2. myles aboue Heydelburgh.</p>
            <p>That there are ſome Galleons and Ships ſent out of Spaine and Biſcaine, but what they will doe it is not yet knowne.</p>
            <p>Out of <hi>France</hi> it is certified, that they of Rochell dayly bring Prizes and booties into the Towne and ſtill ſtrengthen themſelues by water. That the King is in the Field with 3. Armies. It is ſaid that Roane is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged, and that there is great ſpeed made to beſiege Rochell both by Water and by Land, but they of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chell make preparation to withſtand it.</p>
            <p>It is alſo certified, that the King hath taken <hi>Roane</hi> by Compoſition, as alſo <hi>Truingo,</hi> and that they marched to St. <hi>Foy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is certified that the Oſtenders at Sea, kept 2. and 2. together, and that the Holland<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s Ships follow them and haue driuen of them on ground in England, and we heare another of them is caſt away.</p>
            <p>The Netherland Souldiers out of diuers parts are all march'd vpwards, and our Ships with Ordnance, Bridges, and other Munition are gone higher to and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4603:10"/>before Bommell.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="account">
            <head>A Letter from Mainheim, dated the <hi>24.</hi> of May. <hi>1622.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MY laſt Letter was on the 14. of May, in which I gaue you to vnderſtand of the Archduke <hi>Leopoldus</hi> his ſhamefull retreate from Hage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naw and of his loſſe there of Munition eſpecially. The King and Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> marched downe againe to <hi>Spires,</hi> there the Marqueſſe of Baden met them, whereupon Conſultation it was concluded, that the King &amp; Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> ſhould paſſe ouer the Rhine and Necker before at this Towne as they did the day before yeſterday, and will be this night in the Land of Darmeſtat, if God permit.</p>
            <p>And the Marqueſſe of <hi>Baden</hi> is paſſed the Rhine ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterday as was agreed at Germerſheim, and to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row will repaſſe it heere againe with his Army, and follow the King: which ſeperation was a bolde and braue Aduenture, yet is like to ſpeed well as ſuch doe often in Warre, for <hi>Don Gouſa</hi> hath ſent 25. Coronets of Cauallery to Monſieur <hi>Tilly,</hi> who lyeth ſtill about Heydelburgh as farr as we heare, and will not meddle with the Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Mansfield</hi> and the Marques of Baden, if they be once ioyned, ſeeing it appeares that <hi>Cordou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> will not ſtirre out of his Garriſons with his Infantry. But I would the Marques were with the King, hee for his perſon behaued himſelfe exceeding brauely, as I heare ſince from the mouthes of his Enemies, and ſo
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4603:10"/>did his two younger Sonnes alſo, who are now alſo with him, beſides the loſſe of all his Baggage, Artille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Munition, his men flung away their Armes in their flight, but he hath furniſhed them againe, by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arming his Subiects.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> is on foot, and like to goe to Bauaria rather then come hither as I heare, and is feared by the way, he takes thorow the Land of <hi>Algſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> to ſpare which he hath bin offered 100. Thouſand Dollers, but would haue 50. Thouſand more. The Duke of <hi>Bauaria</hi> is going I heare to forme a Campe about <hi>Dunaner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to reſiſt him, and the Elector of <hi>Saxon</hi> is drawing his Forces together in <hi>Turning,</hi> to the ſame end alſo as it is thought, but hee will make his part good, vnleſſe Monſieur <hi>Tilly</hi> goe from hence to helpe him, and if hee doe, the Prieſts and Shauelings and their helpers are like to goe to wracke.</p>
            <p>It is reported that the Towne of Collen before this, did ayde <hi>Spinola</hi> with 50. thouſand Dollers, and that now alſo the Hollanders will haue aſmuch of the ſame Towne, what will enſue thereof we ſhall heare.</p>
            <p>From Bruſſels it is certified, that the Earle of <hi>Swat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zenburgh</hi> the Emperours Ambaſſadour is arriued there out of England, and yet ſtayes there, as alſo an Ambaſſadour out of England, and that they haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to enter into a treaty. That the Counteſſe of <hi>Bucquoy,</hi> with her Sonne <hi>Albertus,</hi> and the Earle <hi>Biglia</hi> her Brother, were ready to depart from thence with <hi>Don Iean Heruaert,</hi> to goe to Vienna, and carry the Duke of Lichtenſtein, and the Earle of Megen the Golden Fleece.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:4603:11"/>
            <p>From the Eaſt Countrey it is written, that the King of Denmarke, hath ſent Ambaſſadours to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and the Duke of Saxon, to bee a meanes to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure Peace to be made in the Empire, and that the Palatinate may be reſtored againe, In the meane time the ſaid King takes vp a great number of Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in the Land of Holſt, Denmarke, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, and 3. Peſants are forced to ſet out one Souldier.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4603:11"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
